#### tomrjoyner@gmail.com 0450 703 042

# Tom Joyner

# Digital journalist

I am a driven journalist with a varied experience in online media and reporting. I have a fierce interest in digital storytelling in particular. I have spent the start of my career working in print and online journalism, where I have developed strong newsgathering and research skills and a keen work ethic. I have a particular interest in using freedom of information legislation in my reporting.

# @tomrjoyner http://tomjoyner.github.io

## Work experience

#### **Australian Broadcasting Corporation**

Digital journalist and producer (Oct 16 – present)

Based in the Ultimo newsroom, I write news articles, analysis, and background explainers for ABC News Online. I regularly generate my own ideas and am expected to pitch, research and file written and photographic work of high quality to deadline with minimal supervision. I am expected to have a solid understanding of the online news environment. I also work directly with ABC radio journalists around Australia to convert their stories for the web.

### **Australian Broadcasting Corporation**

Web publisher (Sep 2014 - Oct 2016)

As part of the Radio Current Affairs division, I was responsible for writing and publishing online story summaries for AM, The World Today and PM on the ABC website. I also managed the programs' public Facebook and Twitter accounts, posting content to over 60,000 followers multiple times daily.

#### **Honi Soit**

Editor (Dec 2015 - Dec 2016)

As one member in a team of 10 editors, I was responsible for the weekly print and online production of the University of Sydney's student newspaper. Each week, we managed a team of over 100 regular reporters in soliciting news and opinion pitches, drafting articles, subediting, and designing a final product.

#### The Sydney Morning Herald

Editorial intern (Jan 2016 - Feb 2016)

Over a six week placement at major Sydney masthead The Sydney Morning Herald I regularly filed news for the state desk for both print and online. I routinely demonstrated an independent work ethic in sourcing and following up my own stories, developing a list of contacts and working to deadline.

#### The Australian

Editorial intern (Mar 2016 - Aug 2016)

I wrote for the higher education section of The Australian newspaper and given autonomy to pursue stories of my own accord, filing to a strict print deadline each week. I was required to have a deep understanding of the tertiary education sector, and covered many issues ranging from university funding to social media for academics. I was during my time there commended on my timeliness and writing skills by then higher education editor, Julie Hare.

#### **The Canberra Times**

Editorial intern (Feb 2015)

During a two week placement at The Canberra Times I filed news for both print and online with minimal guidance, including three front page stories. Among these was a story on ACT public housing I successfully pitched, researched and filed on my own. While there, I was highly commended by the editor and chief of staff.

#### **Bull Magazine**

Editor (Dec 2014 - Dec 2015)

As part of a five-member team of editors, I was responsible for the print and online publishing of the University of Sydney Union's monthly student magazine. For 12 months, we oversaw the pitching, drafting, editing, sub-editing and final publishing of articles, artwork, puzzles and photography from students across campus. We worked with the Union's staff to design and lay up the final product.

#### **Broadsheet**

Editorial intern (Jan 2014 - Sep 2014)

During an eight-month placement at food and culture website Broadsheet, I wrote news, features and restaurant reviews for a Sydney audience. I developed contacts in the Sydney dining industry and honed interview skills to produce high quality writing in a short turnaround.

#### **Skills**

#### **Photography**

Highly developed skills in digital and analogue photography, photojournalism, photo processing and event photography.

#### Freedom of information

Drafting, lodging and appealing requests under the Commonwealth, ACT, Victoria, Queensland and NSW acts. I have also previously handled external appeals with the NSW Information and Privacy Commission and the Office of the Information Commissioner.

#### Social media

Experience managing official Twitter and Facebook public channels with over 60,000 followers, including writing engaging posts and comment moderation.

#### Multimedia

Video and audio recording and editing to broadcast quality in Final Cut Pro X, Reaper and Netia. Further experience using Adobe software, including Illustrator, InDesign and Photoshop.

#### Web

Experience using online content management tools such as WordPress, Wallace, Django, CQ and Core Media. Further experience in touch typing, transcription, sub-editing, SEO, and Microsoft Office. Basic programming skills using HTML and CSS to build static websites and scraper tools.

#### Education

#### **University of Sydney**

Bachelor of International and Global Studies (Government and International Relations)

Expected graduation at end of 2017

#### References

#### Will Ockenden

Digital projects
Australian Broadcasting Corporation
(02) 8333 2214
ockenden.will@abc.net.au

#### **Ben Hays**

Executive producer Australian Broadcasting Corporation (07) 3377 5489 hays.ben@abc.net.au

#### Monique Ross

Executive producer Australian Broadcasting Corporation (07) 3377 5489 ross.monique@abc.net.au

#### Joel Zander

Executive producer Australian Broadcasting Corporation (07) 3377 5489 zander.joel@abc.net.au